consider a large electrically charged
sphere with a charge capital Q and A
small sphere with a charge small q the
electric force between these two spheres
which are at the distance R from each
other is given by colum's law here 1/ 4
Pi epsilon0 is a constant preactor with
the electric field constant Epsilon 0
which provides the right unit of force
the unit Newton now what if you know the
value of the big charge and want to know
the value of the force that the big
charge exerts on the small charge
however you do not know the exact value
of this little charge or you
intentionally leave that value open and
only want to look at the electric force
exerted by the big charge so you have to
somehow eliminate the small charge Q
from colum's law to do so you simply
divide colum's law by Q on both sides
this way on the right hand side the
small charge drops out and instead lands
on the left hand side of the equation
the quotient on the left hand side F
over Q is defined as the electric field
e of the source charge Q by calling it
Source charge we imply that the charge Q
is the source of the electric field the
electric field e thus indicates the
electric force which would act on a
small charge when placed at the distance
R to the source charge